"The Side Effects of the Hormones in Milk"
We've known for decades
that women who eat meat
have higher levels of estrogen
in their blood.
Compared to nonvegetarians,
vegetarian women were found
to have 45 percent lower levels
of the most potent
human estrogen.
This may help explain
the lower incidence
of breast cancer
among those eating
more plant-based.
Even semi-vegetarians
who eat less meat
than omnivorous women
may have significantly lower
estrogen levels.
Why?
Perhaps because
vegetarian women excrete
two to three times
more estrogens in their feces
than do
their meat-eating counterparts.
And why is that?
Because the average
fecal output of vegetarians
can be twice as high.
Look at those heavyweight Vs
compared to
the featherweight Os.
The thought is that
because vegetarians eat
the amount of fiber
closer to that
which is natural
for our species,
those relying more on plants
have an increased fecal output,
which helps pull
excess estrogen
out of the system.
It may also have
something to do
with the hormones present
in animal products.
For example, the higher average
blood concentrations
of estrogen
associated
with high dairy consumption
would be consistent with milk
as a major source of estrogens
in the human diet.
The reason we're concerned is
that the increased consumption
of animal-derived foods
may have adverse effects
on the development
of hormone-dependent cancers.
Among dietary risk factors,
these investigators
were most concerned
about milk and dairy products,
because the milk we drink today
is produced by pregnant cows
with markedly elevated levels
of both estrogen
and progesterone.
The genetic manipulation
of dairy cows
enables them to lactate
throughout almost
their entire pregnancies,
which is why
commercial cow's milk
contains large amounts
of estrogens
and progesterone these days.
That may be why milk-drinkers
have five times the rates
of having twins
compared to vegans.
That's how much of an effect
dairy may have on our hormones.
But we don't really know how
much the hormones in dairy
affects our hormones
until we put it to the test.
Researchers looked to see
what happens
when men
and prepubescent children,
who both would normally have
low estrogen levels,
chug a quart (950 ml)
of cow's milk
in under ten minutes.
This is what happened
to the men.
Within an hour
of drinking the milk,
their levels of the estrogen
estrone went up (and progesterone),
and testosterone significantly
dropped within 60 minutes.
It's funny, there are men
who don't want
to drink soy milk
because of the phytoestrogens,
even though soy phytoestrogens
normally does not have
feminizing effects on men,
yet they're perfectly willing
to drink cow's milk,
which has actual
estrogen estrogens in it!
In children, researchers saw
the same thing.
The level of estrogens
flowing through their body
within an hour of drinking milk
more than tripled:
estrone, the potent estrogen
estradiol,
the pregnancy estrogen estriol,
and a progesterone metabolite.
And half the kids
couldn't even finish
the whole quart (950 ml)
of milk.
There's also another
sex steroid hormone
present in cow's milk
called 5alpha-P
(5alpha-pregnenedione)
which is a direct precursor
to a type of testosterone
that may not only drive acne
but also promote
prostate cancer.
Now, we'd like to see
controlled clinical studies,
but the problem is
there is no control.
Dairy without the offending
estrogens does not exist.
Even organic milk from cows
who aren't injected
with extra hormones
has growth hormones in it,
because biologically,
that's the whole point of milk,
to put a couple of hundred
pounds on a baby calf.
The problem with humans
drinking cow hormones
is that there's
no natural feedback loop.
For our own hormones,
if we have too much estrogen
or something,
our brain dampens it down.
But our own protective
feedback system is bypassed
when our system is invaded
by these dihydrotestosterone
precursors
in dairy products.
See, the human
endocrine system,
our hormonal system,
didn't evolve
under the influence
of ingested dairy
and other external hormones
and growth factors,
and we're just not equipped
to cope with such
a quote-unquote "sneak attack."
In summary, evidence suggests
that consumption
of dairy-sourced hormones,
which aren't subject to any
innate feedback inhibition,
may be the source
of the steroid sex hormones
that drive acne
and at least prostate cancer.
This is perhaps the most
promising unifying hypothesis—
or theory—
to explain the cause
of diverse conditions
that blemish, scar, shorten,
or take the lives of millions.